《夺宝奇兵3：圣战奇兵》
下马
Dismount!
赫曼的马病了
Herman's horse-sick!
小伙子们  千万不要乱跑
Chaps, no one wander off.
有些小径绵延数里远
Some of the passageways in here can run for miles.
我不觉得这是个好点子
I don't think this is such a good idea.
那是什么声音？
What is it?
- 阿尔弗雷德  你找到了什么吗？ - 还没有
- Alfred, did you get anything yet? - Nothing.
那就继续挖
Then keep digging.
那小鬼找到东西了
The kid's got something!
我找到东西了  费多拉
I got something, Garth! I got something...
这里有东西
I got something right here.
你看
Look at that!
- 我们要发财了  - 闭嘴
- We're rich! We're rich!    - Shut up. Shut up.
我们要发财了 是不是？
Well, we're rich, ain't we?
印第
Indy...
Indy?
他们在做什么？
What are they doing?
印第安纳...
Indiana? Indiana?
(犹他州  1912年)
我们得找到其他的东西
Hey, we got to find more stuff to bring back.
这是科罗芮多的十字架
It's the Cross of Coronado.
科尔特斯人1520年送他的礼物
Cortez gave it to him in 1520.
我要把这枚戒指送给我妈  把它戴在她瘦巴巴的手指头上
I'm thinkin' about raisin' my dead mama, dig down and put it on her bony finger!
那个十字架是很重要的古物  它是博物馆的财产
That cross is an important artifact. It belongs in a museum.
跑回去  找到其他人
Run back and find the others.
告诉海拉克先生  有人在洞穴里偷东西
Tell Mr. Havelock that there are men looting in the caves.
请他去通知警长  蛇没什么好怕的
Have him bring the sheriff. It's only a snake.
听到了没？
Did you hear what I said?
很好  跑回去
Right. Run back...
找海拉克先生  请他通知警长
Mr. Havelock... The sheriff...
你打算怎么办？
What, what are you gonna do?
不知道
I don't know.
我会想出办法来的
I'll think of something.
快点把东西挖出来  别聊天了
Dig with your hands, not with your mouth.
他拿走了我们的东西
He's got our thing!
- 抓住他   - 别挡道
- Get him!    - Get off me!
海拉克先生  快来人
Mr. Havelock! Anybody!
他们丢下我逃跑了
Everybody's lost but me.
他在那里  快一点
There he is! Let's go! Let's go!
- 别跑  - 我们一定会抓到你
- Hey! Hey, you! - Dang it!
快回来
Hey! Come back here!
快点  抓住他
Come on! Get him!
快回来
Hey, come back here!
(唐恩与多菲马戏团)
(全世界最高的长颈鹿)
(蛇窝)
闪开  让我来吧
Here, let me.
我的天啊
Holy smokes!
放弃吧  孩子
Come on, kid.
你是插翅难飞了
There's no way out of this.
嘿
Hey!
快把鞭子丢上来
Toss up the whip.
你拿到了 小鬼  那是我的东西
You got heart, kid, but that belongs to me.
那是科罗芮多的东西
It belongs to Coronado.
他跟他的子孙们都死了
Coronado is dead, and so are all of his grandchildren.
它应该被送进博物馆
This should be in a museum.
快还给我
Now give it back!
是蛇
A snake! Snake!
别让他逃了
Don't let him get away!
魔术小屋？
Magic?
且慢
Hold it.
别又让他溜掉了
Make sure he doesn't double back.
小鬼  快出来
Okay, kid, out of the box, now.
混蛋
Son of a...
该死
Damn.
爸
Dad!
Dad.
- 爸  - 出去
- Dad...    - Out.
- 这件事很重要   - 等一下  你先数到二十
- It's important. - Then wait. Count to 20.
- 不  听我说  - 二世
- No, Dad. You listen to me.   - Junior!
一  二  三  四...
One, two, three, four...
用希腊文数
In Greek.
愿万能的上帝能启发我的心灵
"May he who illuminated this, illuminate me."
我把警长带来了
I brought the sheriff.
我正好要找他
Just the man I want to see.
有五到六个人...
Now, there were five or six of them...
- 好了  孩子  - 他们在追我...
- It's all right, son. - They came after me...
- 东西还在你身上吗？ - 还在
- You still got it? - Well, yes, sir.
就在这里
It's right here.
这下我就安心了
I'm glad to see that
只要你愿意物归原主  原来的物主就不会告你
because the rightful owner of this cross won't press charges if you give it back.
他有五到六个目击证人
He's got witnesses, five or six of them.
耶
Yeah!
再见
Good day.
今天你输了  孩子
You lost today, kid,
但这不代表你得心甘情愿地接受事实
but it doesn't mean you have to like it.
(1938年  葡萄牙海岸)
世界还真小  琼斯博士
Small world, Dr. Jones.
我们又见面了
Too small for two of us.
我以前就曾从你手上拿回属于我的东西
This is the second time I've had to reclaim my property from you.
那应该被送进博物馆
That belongs in a museum.
你也一样
So do you.
把他丢下去
Throw him over the side.
抓住他  他要逃跑了
Grab him, he's getting away! Stop him!
(科罗芮多号)
考古学要寻找的是事实
Archeology is the search for fact...
而非真相
...not truth.
如果你们想要寻找真相
If it's truth you're interested in,
哲学课教室在走廊底下
Dr. Tyree's philosophy class is right down the hall.
别梦想着要寻找失落的城市  到世界各地旅行
So forget any ideas you've got about lost cities, exotic travel,
挖掘古物
and digging up the world.
我们不会照地图找宝藏
We do not follow maps to buried treasure,
打了"X"的地方不会有实物
and "X" never, ever, marks the spot.
七成的考古学研究  都是在图书馆里完成
Seventy percent of all archeology is done in the library.
研究  找资料...
Research. Reading.
我们不能片面地看待神话
We cannot afford to take mythology at face value.
下星期要上埃及古物学
Next week, Egyptology,
和1885年诺克拉提斯大撤离
starting with the excavation of Naukratis by Flinders Petrie in 1885.
有问题的话  你们可以到办公室来找我
I will be in my office if anybody's got any problems, for the next hour and a half.
马库斯  我成功了
Marcus, I did it.
你真的拿到手了
You've got it!
你知道我找它找了多久吗？
You know how long I've been looking for that?
你花了一辈子的时间
All your life.
一点都没错
All my life.
这真的是太棒了
Well done, Indy. Very well done, indeed.
它将会成为西班牙专区的收集品之一
This will find a place of honor in our Spanish collection.
我们可以边吃晚餐边喝香槟  好好讨论我的酬劳
We can discuss my honorarium over dinner and champagne tonight.
- 你请客  - 好吧
- Your treat.    - Yes.
我请客
My treat.
- 琼斯博士  - 琼斯博士
- Dr. Jones! - Dr. Jones!
很高兴你回来了
Dr. Jones, I am so glad you're back.
信件全放在你的桌上  这是你的电话留言
Your mail is on your desk. Here are your phone messages.
琼斯博士  你答应过...
Dr. Jones, you promised...
这是你的日程表
This is your appointment schedule,
这些考卷还没有改好
and these term papers still haven't been graded.
爱琳  把每个人的名字登记下来...
Okay. Irene, put everybody's name on a list, get the order they arrived...
- 拜托  琼斯博士  - 琼斯博士
- Oh, come on, Dr. Jones. - Dr. Jones.
我会照顺序亲自跟他们每个人谈话
...and I'll see each and every one of them in turn.
"意大利威尼斯"
"Venice, Italy."
琼斯博士
Dr. Jones!
Dr. Jones?
琼斯博士
Dr. Jones.
我想这一路你应该还蛮舒服的  琼斯博士
I trust your trip down was comfortable, Dr. Jones.
希望我的手下没吓到你
My men didn't alarm you, I hope.
我是华特·陶诺文
My name is Donovan. Walter Donovan.
我认识你
I know who you are, Mr. Donovan.
你对博物馆贡献良多
Your contributions to the museum over the years have been extremely generous.
你的收藏品令人留下深刻印象
Some of the pieces in your collection here are very impressive.
我跟你一样非常喜欢古文物
Well, like yourself, Dr. Jones, I have a passion for antiquities.
请过来这边看看
Have a look over here.
你可能会有兴趣
This might interest you.
这是砂岩板  基督教的圣物
Well, it's sandstone. Christian symbol.
内容以古希腊文写成
Early Latin text.
是十二世纪中期古物
Mid-12th century, I should think.
我们也那么认为
That was our assessment, as well.
你在哪里找到它的？
Where did this come from?
我的工程师在安卡拉北部挖铜时
My engineers unearthed it in the mountain region north of Ankara
意外地发现了它
while excavating for copper.
你能翻译出铭文的内容吗？
Can you translate the inscription?
上帝说  "喝下这水的人 我会赐福给他"
"...who drinks the water I shall give him, says the Lord,
"让他拥有源源不绝的力量"
"will have a spring inside him
"获得长生不死的恩惠"
"welling up for eternal life."
"让它们带我走向你居住的圣山"
"Let them bring me to your holy mountain in the place where you dwell."
"越过沙漠  爬过高山"
"Across the desert and through the mountain
"进入新月峡谷"
"to the Canyon of the Crescent Moon,
"进入安放圣杯的神殿"
"to the temple where the cup that...
"装了耶稣基督之血的圣杯 将永远地安放于此"
"Where the cup that holds the blood of Jesus Christ resides forever."
它指的是圣杯  琼斯博士
The Holy Grail, Dr. Jones.
耶稣在最后的晚餐中用过的杯子
The chalice used by Christ during the Last Supper.
当耶稣被钉上十字架时  它被拿来接住耶稣的血
The cup that caught His blood at the Crucifixion
之后交由亚利马太的约瑟保管
and was entrusted to Joseph of Arimathea.
还扯上了亚瑟王的故事
The Arthur legend.
我听过这些童话故事
I've heard this bedtime story before.
用圣杯来喝东西
Eternal life, Dr. Jones!
便可以获得长生不老的力量
The gift of youth to whoever drinks from the Grail.
我很喜欢这种童话故事
Now, that's a bedtime story I'd like to wake up to.
它也是一个老人的梦想
An old man's dream.
更是每一个人的希望  我相信这也包括了你父亲在内
Every man's dream, including your father's, I believe.
研究圣杯是他的嗜好
Grail lore is his hobby.
他是中世纪文学教师
He's a teacher of medieval literature.
但学生们都讨厌他
The one the students hope they don't get.
你冷落了客人们
Walter, you're neglecting your guests.
我马上来  亲爱的
Be along in a moment, dear.
这真的很难抵抗吧？
Hard to resist, isn't it?
它详细记载了圣杯的最后落脚处
The Holy Grail's final resting place described in detail.
它根本就没有用
What good is it?
石碑提到了沙漠  高山和峡谷
This Grail tablet speaks of deserts and mountains and canyons.
范围太模糊了
It's pretty vague.
你打算从哪里开始找？
Where do you want to start looking?
只可惜石碑破了
Maybe if the tablet were intact, you'd have something to go on,
上半部整个都不见了
but the entire top portion is missing.
但我们还是可以展开行动  寻找圣杯的下落
Just the same, an attempt to recover the Grail is currently underway.
我要再告诉你一个故事
Let me tell you another bedtime story, Dr. Jones.
圣杯交给约瑟保管后
After the Grail was entrusted to Joseph of Arimathea,
一千年来始终找不到它的下落
it disappeared, and was lost for a thousand years
最后在第一次十字军东征中 有三个骑士发现了圣杯的下落
before it was found again by three knights of the First Crusade.
确切地说  是三兄弟
Three brothers, to be exact.
我也听过这个故事
I've heard this one, as well.
一百五十年后
Two of these brothers walked out of the desert
三兄弟之中的两个人走出沙漠
150 years after having found the Grail
他们打算回到法国
and began the long journey back to France,
但只有一个人撑了下来
but only one of them made it.
当时已经垂垂老矣的他在临终前说出了圣杯的下落
And before dying of extreme old age,
传说他把自己的故事告诉了圣方济会的修士
he supposedly imparted his tale to a... to a Franciscan friar, I think.
那不是传说  琼斯博士
Not "supposedly," Dr. Jones.
在这份文稿中  修士记载了骑士的故事
This is the manuscript in which the friar chronicled the knight's story.
虽然没有明白指出圣杯的下落
It doesn't reveal the location of the Grail, I'm afraid,
但骑士保证这两条线索
but the knight promised that two markers
能告诉我们它在哪里
that had been left behind would.
这个石碑就是线索之一
This tablet is one of those markers.
它证明了骑士的故事是真的
It proves the knight's story is true.
可惜石碑破了
But as you pointed out, it's incomplete.
第二条线索 在他死去兄弟的坟墓中
Now, the second marker is entombed with the knight's dead brother.
圣杯计划的负责人相信  这座坟墓就在意大利威尼斯
Our project leader believes that tomb to be located within the city of Venice, Italy.
你应该可以了解
As you can now see, Dr. Jones,
我们即将完成这个伟大使命
we're about to complete a great quest
这场寻找之旅有近两千年的历史
that began almost 2,000 years ago.
现在我们差一步就能成功
We're only one step away.
那也是最常尝到失败滋味的时候
That's usually when the ground falls out from underneath your feet.
你说的没错
You could be more right than you know.
是吗？
Yes?
我们遇到了大麻烦
We've hit a snag.
这项计划的负责人突然失踪  他的研究成果也消失不见
Our project leader has vanished, along with all his research.
他的同事史奈德博士
We received a cable from his colleague, Dr. Schneider,
不知道他的下落
who has no idea of his whereabouts or what's become of him.
我要你接替他的任务
I want you to pick up the trail where he left off.
只要能找到他  就能找到圣杯
Find the man, and you will find the Grail.
你找错人了  陶诺文先生
You've got the wrong Jones, Mr. Donovan.
你为什么不去找我老爸呢？
Why don't you try my father?
我们已经找过他了
We already have.
你父亲就是那位失踪的负责人
Your father is the man who has disappeared.
你父亲跟我是多年好友
Your father and I have been friends since time began.
我是看着你长大的
I've watched you grow up, Indy.
也是看着你们俩分开的
I've watched the two of you grow apart.
我从来没看过你这么担心他
I've never seen you this concerned about him before.
老爸？
Dad?
他是个学者  不是个冒险家
He's an academic, a bookworm. He's not a field man.
爸？
Dad?
我的老天爷
Dear God.
那个老笨蛋  帮自己惹上了什么样的麻烦
What has the old fool got himself into now?
我不知道  不管发生了什么事 他一定是疯了
I don't know, but whatever it is, he's in over his head.
老爸？
Dad?
这是今天收到的信件  信被拆开过了
It's today's mail, and it's been opened.
信件...
Mail.
就是这个  马库斯
That's it, Marcus.
"意大利威尼斯"
Venice, Italy.
那是什么东西？
What is it?
我老爸的圣杯日记
It's Dad's Grail diary.
记载着他找到的每一条线索和他所有的发现
Every clue he followed. Every discovery he made.
完整地记录了他寻找圣杯的经过
A complete record of his search for the Holy Grail.
这是他一生的心血
This is his whole life.
他为什么要把它寄给我？
Why would he have sent this to me?
我不知道
I don't know,
但一定有人在觊觎这本日记
but someone must want it pretty badly.
你相信吗 马库斯？
Do you believe, Marcus?
你相信圣杯真的存在吗？
Do you believe the Grail actually exists?
事实上寻找圣杯就是在寻找人类的神性
The search for the Cup of Christ is the search for the divine in all of us.
如果你要的是事实  我没办法告诉你答案
But if you want facts, Indy, I've none to give you.
我已经一把年纪了  我打算相信上帝真的存在
At my age, I'm prepared to take a few things on faith.
打电话通知陶诺文
Call Donovan, Marcus.
我会立刻搭飞机到威尼斯
Tell him I'll take that ticket to Venice now.
我会告诉他我们需要两张机票
I'll tell him we'll take two.
我们到了威尼斯后呢？
All right, tell me what's going to happen when we get to Venice.
史奈德博士会去接你们
Don't worry, Dr. Schneider will be there to meet you.
- 史奈德？ - 你们可以住在我在威尼斯的公寓
- Schneider?    - I maintain an apartment in Venice. It's at your disposal.
很好  谢谢
Oh, well, that's good. Thank you.
琼斯博士  祝你好运
Dr. Jones, good luck.
小心点  别相信任何人
Now be very careful. Don't trust anybody.
(纽约)
(纽芬兰)
(亚速群岛)
(里斯本)
(威尼斯)
- 这就是威尼斯  - 没错
- Ah, Venice...   - Yes.
哪一位是史奈德博士？
How will we recognize this Dr. Schneider when we see him?
我不知道  或许他会认得我们
I don't know. Maybe he'll know us.
你是琼斯博士吗？
Dr. Jones?
是的
Yes?
我就知道是你
I knew it was you.
你有着你父亲的眼睛
You have your father's eyes.
我还有我妈妈的耳朵  至于其他的都是你的了
And my mother's ears, but the rest belongs to you.
但最棒的都被别人拿走了
Looks like the best parts have already been spoken for.
- 你就是马库斯·布鲁迪？ - 没错
- Marcus Brody? - That's right.
我是艾儿莎·史奈德博士
Dr. Elsa Schneider.
你好吗？
How do you do?
我最后一次见到你父亲  是在图书馆里
The last time I saw your father, we were in the library.
他就快要找到坟墓了
He was very close to tracking down the knight's tomb.
我从来没见过他如此兴奋
I've never seen him so excited.
他跟小学生一样笑个不停
He was as giddy as a schoolboy.
你说那个铁血教授？
Who? Attila the Professor?
他从来不会笑个不停  即使他真的只是个小学生
He was never giddy, even when he was a schoolboy.
美丽的小姐  请收下吧
Freulein, will you permit me?
- 通常我是不会答应的  - 通常我也不会这么做
- I usually don't. - I usually don't, either.
- 那么我就收下了  - 这会令我高兴的
- In that case, I permit you.    - It would make me very happy.
我已经开始伤心了  到了明天  它就会凋谢
But I'm already sad. By tomorrow, it will have faded.
明天我再送你一个
Tomorrow I'll steal you another.
我不想打断你们  但是...
I hate to interrupt you, but the reason we're here...
有样东西我希望你能看一下
Yes. I have something to show you.
我留你父亲自己在图书馆工作
I left your father working in the library.
当时他请我去拿旧都市计划图
He sent me to the map section to fetch an ancient plan of the city.
我回来时发现他跟文件不见了
When I got back to his table, he'd gone, with all his papers,
只剩下这张纸  在他的椅子旁边发现的
except for that scrap, which I found near his chair.
是罗马数字
Roman numerals.
图书馆到了
Here is the library.
它看起来一点都不像图书馆
That doesn't look much like a library.
比较像是教堂
Looks like a converted church.
一点都没错
In this case, it's the literal truth.
你们来到了圣地
We are on holy ground.
这些柱子饱受战火蹂躏  之后被送来这里
These columns over here were brought back as spoils of war
在十字军东征时 拜占庭帝国饱受战争之苦
after the sacking of Byzantium during the Crusades.
抱歉
Now, please excuse me.
图书馆快关门了
The library's closing in a few moments.
我会去安排让我们再待一会
I'll arrange for us to stay a little longer.
马库斯  我看过这扇窗户
Marcus, I've seen this window before.
在哪里？
Where?
就在老爸的日记里
Right here, in Dad's diary.
看到了没？
You see?
你看  印第  是罗马数字
Look, Indy. The Roman numerals.
老爸真的找到了线索
Dad was onto something here.
但我们不知它们代表什么意思
Well, now we know the source of the numbers, but we still don't know what they mean.
他会把日记寄给我是有原因的
Dad sent me this diary for a reason.
这件事千万别说出去
Until we find out why, I suggest we keep it to ourselves.
有发现吗？
Find something?
三  七跟十
Yes. Three, seven and ten.
窗户上的数字
That window seems to be the source of the Roman numerals.
我真的太粗心了
My God, I must be blind.
他要找的并不是记载坟墓的书
Dad wasn't looking for a book about the knight's tomb,
而是坟墓本身
he was looking for the tomb itself.
你找到了吗？
Don't you get it?
坟墓就在图书馆里
The tomb is somewhere in the library.
你说过这里以前是教堂
You said yourself it used to be a church.
你看
Look.
三
Three.
七...
Seven.
七  十
Seven. Ten.
十
And ten.
十在哪里？
Now where's the ten?
找一找十在哪里
Look around for the ten.
三跟七...
Three and seven.
七跟七...
Seven and seven
十
and ten.
Ten.
"X"就是坟墓的地点
"X" marks the spot.
找到了
Bingo.
你真的很行  琼斯博士
You don't disappoint, Dr. Jones.
你就跟你父亲一样
You're a great deal like your father.
但他失踪了  我还在
Except he's lost, and I'm not.
快来帮帮我
Lower me down.
帮我看好它
Look after this for me, will you?
快一点
Come on.
四或五世纪的异教徒符号
Pagan symbols. Fourth or fifth century.
没错
Right.
年代是十字军东征前六百年
600 years before the Crusades.
几个世纪后
The Christians would have dug their own passages
基督徒挖掘了属于他们的通道
and burial chambers centuries later.
没错
That's right.
如果第一次十字军东征骑士真的埋在这里
If there's a knight of the First Crusade down here,
他一定在那边
that's where we'll find him.
这是什么东西？
What's this one?
约柜
The Ark of the Covenant.
- 你确定？ - 非常确定
- Are you sure?    - Pretty sure.
小心
Watch out.
是石油
It's petroleum.
我该退休到这里来挖油井
I should sink a well down here and retire.
把打火机拿过来
Give me the lighter.
是老鼠
Oh, rats.
快来吧
Come on.
这边
Come here.
你看  他一定在这些棺木之中
Look, it... it must be one of these.
你看看  这些雕刻跟铭文有多漂亮
Look at the artistry of these carvings, and the scrollwork.
就是这具棺木
It's this one.
没错  我们找到它了
This is it. We found it.
你看
Look.
盾牌上的铭文跟圣杯石碑的铭文是一样的
The engraving on the shield, it's the same as on the Grail tablet.
这面盾牌是第二条线索
The shield is the second marker.
那是什么？
What's that?
这是我爸从圣杯石碑上拓印下来的
It's a rubbing Dad made of the Grail tablet.
你就像你父亲一样  兴奋地笑个不停
Just like your father, giddy as a schoolboy.
如果他能亲自到这里来  那就真的是太棒了
Wouldn't it be wonderful if he were here now to see this?
他没办法过老鼠那一关
He never would have made it past the rats.
他最害怕的东西就是老鼠
He hates rats. He's scared to death of them.
快退回墙边
Get back! Back against the wall.
快趴下  吸气
Quick! Under it! Air pocket!
- 别走开  - 什么？
- Don't wander off.   - What?
什么？
What?
我找到出路了
I think I've found a way out.
深呼吸
Deep breath.
这就是威尼斯
Ah, Venice.
你疯了吗？别从中间穿过去
Are you crazy? Don't go between them!
从中间穿过去？你疯了吗？
Go between them? Are you crazy?
我叫你绕过去
I said go around!
你叫我从中间穿过去
You said go between them!
我叫你别从中间穿过去
I said, don't go between them!
不
No!
你为什么要杀我们？
Why are you trying to kill us?
因为你们要找圣杯
Because you're looking for the Holy Grail.
你也杀了我父亲吗？
My father was looking for the Holy Grail. Did you kill him too?
没有
No.
他在哪里？
Where is he?
快说  不然你就死定了
Talk or you're dead.
该死  快告诉我
Damn it, tell me!
告诉我
Tell me!
你不放手的话  我们都会死
If you don't let go, Dr. Jones, we'll both die.
那我们就一起死吧
Then we'll die.
我已经准备好受死了  你呢？
My soul is prepared. How's yours?
这是你的最后机会
This is your last chance.
不  这是你的最后机会
No, Dr. Jones, it's yours.
好吧  我父亲在哪里？
All right, where's my father?
放了我  我就告诉你
If you let me go, I will tell you where he is.
你是谁？
Who are you?
我叫做卡辛姆
My name is Kazim.
你为什么要杀我？
And why were you trying to kill me?
一千年来 没有人知道圣杯的秘密
The secret of the Grail has been safe for a thousand years,
在这段时间里
and for all that time,
十字剑兄弟会
the Brotherhood of the Cruciform Sword
不计任何代价保护这个秘密
have been prepared to do anything to keep it safe.
让我下船
Let me off at this jetty.
扪心自问一下  为什么你要寻找圣杯？
Ask yourself, why do you seek the Cup of Christ?
你要追求上帝的光荣  还是自己的光荣呢？
Is it for His glory, or for yours?
我要找的不是圣杯  我是来找我的父亲
I didn't come for the Cup of Christ. I came to find my father.
既然如此  上帝会与你同在
In that case, God be with you in your quest.
他就在德奥边境的布蓝瓦德城堡
Your father is being held in the Castle of Brunwald, on the Austrian-German border.
你的头还会痛吗？
How's the head?
好多了  我已经看过了
It's better, now I've seen this.
它是一座城市的名字 "亚力山勒达"
It's the name of a city. "Alexandretta"?
第一次十字军东征的骑士们围攻亚力山勒达
The knights of the First Crusade laid siege to the city of Alexandretta for over a year.
整个城市被破坏殆尽
The entire city was destroyed.
现在的伊斯肯德隆就盖在该城的遗迹上
The present city of Iskenderun is built on its ruins.
还记得圣杯石碑上是怎么写的吗？
Marcus, you remember what the Grail tablet said,
"越过沙漠  爬过高山"
"Across the desert and through the mountain
"进入新月峡谷"
"to the Canyon of the Crescent Moon."
到底是哪里？
But where exactly?
你父亲一定知道
Your father would know.
你父亲真的知道  你看  他还画了一幅地图
Your father did know. Look. He made a map.
他将寻找圣杯的线索拼凑在一起
He must have pieced it together from clues scattered through the whole history of the Grail quest.
一张无地名地图
A map with no names.
东面有绿洲的城市  就在这里
Now, he knew there was a city with an oasis due east, here.
他知道得由南面进入山区
He knew the course turned south through the desert to a river,
直闯峡谷区
and the river led into the mountains, here. Straight to the canyon.
除了该由哪个城市出发外  他什么都知道
He knew everything except where to begin, the name of the city.
亚力山勒达
Alexandretta.
- 我们知道了  - 没错  现在我们知道了
- Now we know.    - Yes. Now we know.
请萨拉到伊斯肯德隆跟你会合
Marcus, get hold of Sallah. Tell him to meet you in Iskenderun.
你要去哪里？
What about you?
我要去找我爸
I'm going after Dad.
艾儿莎
Elsa?
Elsa? Elsa?
- 我的房间  - 我的也差不多
- My room...   - Mine, too.
他们在找什么？
What were they looking for?
就是这个
This.
圣杯日记
The Grail diary?
它在你手上？
You had it?
你不相信我？
You didn't trust me.
之前我不了解你
I didn't know you.
至少我让你跟着我们跑
At least I let you tag along.
对
Oh, yes.
只要送花给女人  她们就会跟着你跑
Give them a flower, and they'll follow you anywhere.
别这样  你一点都不生气
Knock it off. You're not mad.
真的吗？
No?
当然  你喜欢我的行事作风
No. You like the way I do things.
还好我的行事作风跟你不一样
It's lucky I don't do things the same way.
不然你现在还在威尼斯码头上
You'd still be standing at the Venice pier!
发生了什么事？
Look, what do you think is going on here?
我几乎被烧死跟溺死
Since I met you, I've nearly been incinerated,
还差点被切成碎片当鱼饲料
drowned, shot at, and chopped into fish bait.
我们被拖进一个邪恶计划中
We're caught in the middle of something sinister here.
老爸有了重大的发现
My guess is Dad found out more than he was looking for.
还没有找到他之前
And until I'm sure, I'm going to continue to do things
我会用我的方法来做事
the way I think they should be done.
你胆子真大 竟敢吻我
How dare you kiss me!
放开我  我不喜欢主动的女人
Leave me alone. I don't like fast women.
我讨厌自大的男人
And I hate arrogant men.
我爱威尼斯
Ah, Venice.
(威尼斯)
(萨尔茨堡)
你对这个地方了解多少？
What do you know about this place?
布蓝瓦德家族是艺术收藏家
I know the Brunwalds are famous art collectors.
你打算怎么办？
What are you going to do?
不知道  我会想出办法来
Don't know. I'll think of something.
什么事？
Yes?
你的动作真慢
And not before time!
你打算让我们站在门口吗？
Did you intend to leave us standing on the doorstep all day?
我们全身都湿了
We're drenched!
我一定会感冒鼻塞的
Now look, I've gone and caught a sniffle.
你们有预约吗？
Are you expected?
别用那种语气跟我说话
Do not take that tone with me, my good man.
快通知男爵
Now buttle off and tell Baron Brunwald
克拉伦斯·麦当纳爵爷跟助手
that Lord Clarence MacDonald and his lovely assistant
来看绣帷了
are here to view the tapestries.
看绣帷？
Tapestries?
这家伙蠢呆了
Dear me, the man is dense.
这是一座城堡  对吧？这里有绣帷吗？
This is a castle, isn't it? There are tapestries?
这的确是一座城堡
This is a castle,
我们有很多绣帷
and we have many tapestries.
如果你是苏格兰爵爷  我就是米老鼠
But if you are a Scottish lord, then I am Mickey Mouse!
他真是大胆
How dare he?
是纳粹  我讨厌这些家伙
Nazis. I hate these guys.
我想他就在这里
This one. I think he's in here.
你怎么知道？
How do you know?
因为这里遭到严密监控
Because it's wired.
印第
Indy? Indy?
别担心  小事一件
Don't worry. This is kid's play.
我马上回来
I'll be right back.
二世
Junior?
是我  爸爸
Yes, sir.
你真的来了  二世
It is you, Junior!
请别叫我那个名字
Don't call me that, please.
你来这里做什么？
Well, what are you doing here?
我是来救你的
I came to get you. What do you thi...
十四世纪末期明朝瓷器
Late 14th century, Ming dynasty.
这真是令人伤心
It breaks the heart.
我的头好痛  你竟然打我
And the head. You hit me, Dad.
我永远都不会原谅自己
I'll never forgive myself.
别担心  我没事
Don't worry, I'm fine.
谢天谢地
Thank God.
它是假货
It's fake.
从黏合的地方就可以看出来
See, you can tell by the cross section.
不
No!
我们得离开这里
Dad, get your stuff. We've got to get out of here.
对不起  我打伤了你的头 我还以为你是纳粹
Well, I'm sorry about your head, though, but I thought you were one of them.
爸  他们会从大门进来
Dad, they come in through the doors.
说的好
Good point.
但流汗总比流血好
But better safe than sorry.
这一次我错了
So I was wrong this time.
但把日记寄给你是正确的选择
But, by God, I wasn't wrong when I mailed you my diary.
很明显  你拿到了日记
You obviously got it.
我拿到了日记并好好地利用它
I got it, and I used it.
我们找到了地下墓穴的入口
We found the entrance to the catacombs.
就在图书馆里吗？
Through the library?
没错
Right.
我就知道
I knew it.
理查爵士的坟墓呢？
And the tomb of Sir Richard?
我找到了
Found it.
他真的埋在那里？
He was actually there?
你看到了他？
You saw him?
我只看到他的遗骨
Well, what was left of him.
他的盾牌呢？
And his shield,
理查爵士盾牌上的铭文呢？
the inscription on Sir Richard's shield?
亚力山勒达
"Alexandretta."
亚力山勒达  那是当然的
Alexandretta! Of course!
它就位于东土耳其帝国的朝圣路线上
On the pilgrim trail from the Eastern Empire.
二世  你真的办到了
Junior, you did it.
不  爸  你花了四十年的时间终于办到了
No, Dad. You did. Forty years.
真希望我能跟你一起去
If only I could have been with you.
那里有很多老鼠  爸
There were rats, Dad.
有老鼠？
Rats?
对  又大又肥的老鼠
Yeah, big ones.
纳粹为什么要抓你？
What do the Nazis want with you, Dad?
- 他们想要我的日记  - 什么？
- They wanted my diary.  - Yeah?
我得尽可能让那本日记离开我身边
I knew I had to get that book as far away from me as I possibly could.
没错
Yeah.
琼斯博士
Dr. Jones.
什么事？
Yes?
我现在就要那本书
I will take the book now.
哪本书？
What book?
你口袋里的那本日记
You have the diary in your pocket.
你这个笨蛋
You dolt!
你以为我儿子会那么笨
Do you think my son would be that stupid
把我的日记带回来这里？
that he would bring my diary all the way back here?
你该不会真的那么做了？
You didn't, did you?
- 你没把它带在身上吧？ - 呃...
- You didn't bring it, did you?   - Well...
你真的那么做了
You did.
我们能不能待会再谈？
Look, can we discuss this later?
我该把它寄给马克斯兄弟
I should have mailed it to the Marx Brothers.
别激动
Will you take it easy?
别激动？
Take it easy?
我把它寄回家
Why do you think I sent it home in the first place?
只为了不让它落入坏人手中
So it wouldn't fall into their hands!
我来这里救你
I came here to save you!
真的吗？
Oh, yeah?
谁有办法救你呢  二世？
And who's gonna come to save you, Junior?
我跟你说过
I told you...
别叫我二世
...don't call me Junior!
看看你做的好事
Look what you did!
我不敢相信你竟然...
I can't believe what you did...
艾儿莎
Elsa? Elsa?
够了  快把枪放下
That's far enough. Put down the gun, Dr. Jones.
快把枪放下  不然这位小姐死定了
Put down the gun, or the Freulein dies.
- 她跟他们是一伙的  - 印第 求你了
- But she's one of them.   - Indy, please!
- 她是纳粹  - 什么？
- She's a Nazi.    - What?
- 相信我  - 印第  不
- Trust me.   - Indy, no!
我会杀了她
I will kill her!
- 快动手吧  - 别开枪
- Yeah? Go ahead!  - No! Don't shoot!
别担心  他不会开枪的
Don't worry. He won't.
印第  拜托你照他的话去做
Indy, please! Do what he says!
别听她的
And don't listen to her.
够了  她死定了
Enough! She dies!
等一下
Wait! Wait...
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
不  别说抱歉
No, don't be.
你该听你父亲的话
But you should have listened to your father.
她把自己的房间弄得乱七八糟  我中了她的诡计
She ransacked her own room, and I fell for it.
你怎么知道她是纳粹？
How did you know she was a Nazi?
她睡觉时会说梦话
She talks in her sleep.
我不相信她  你为什么会相信她？
I didn't trust her. Why did you?
因为他没有听进我的话
Because he didn't take my advice.
陶诺文
Donovan.
我不是警告过你别相信任何人吗？
Didn't I warn you not to trust anybody, Dr. Jones?
我看错你了  华特
I misjudged you, Walter.
我就知道  你连自己的母亲都会出卖
I knew you would sell your mother for an Etruscan vase,
但我没想到你会将祖国跟灵魂
but I didn't know you would sell your country and your soul
出卖给这堆人渣
to the slime of humanity.
史奈德博士
Dr. Schneider,
日记里有好几页被撕掉了
there are pages torn out of this.
这本日记里有一张没有地名的地图
This book contained a map, a map with no names,
以及从不知名的城市
precise directions from the unknown city
进入神秘峡谷的路线
to the secret Canyon of the Crescent Moon.
以前的确是那样的
So it did.
被撕掉的那几页在哪里？
Where are these missing pages, this map?
我们要找回那几页
We must have these pages back.
你是在白费口舌
You're wasting your breath.
他不会说的
He won't tell us,
他不必那么做
and he doesn't have to.
我知道那几页在哪里
It's perfectly obvious where the pages are.
他把它们交给了马库斯·布鲁迪
He's given them to Marcus Brody.
马库斯？
Marcus?
你也把他拖来了？
You didn't drag poor Marcus along, did you?
他不是个冒险家
He's not up to the challenge.
他一定会露出马脚
He sticks out like a sore thumb.
我们会逮到他的
We'll find him.
少做梦了
The hell you will.
他已经提前你们两天出发了
He's got a two-day head start on you, which is more than he needs.
到处都有布鲁迪的朋友
Brody's got friends in every town and village
从这到苏丹
from here to the Sudan.
他精通十几种语言
He speaks a dozen languages, knows every local custom.
他会隐身人群中消失不见
He'll blend in, disappear.
你们再也见不到他
You'll never see him again.
如果运气好的话  他应该已经找到圣杯了
With any luck, he's got the Grail already.
有人会说英语或古希腊语吗？
Does anyone here speak English? Or even ancient Greek?
喝水？不用了
Water? No, thank you, sir.
鱼都在水里做爱
No. Fish make love in it.
(伊斯肯德隆)
谢谢你  我真的不需要
Goodness me. Thank you so much. No, I don't like that.
我真不需要
No, I really don't want...
不  谢谢你
No, no, thank you very much.
不用了  我吃素
No, thank you, madam. I'm a vegetarian.
有人听得懂我的话吗？
Does anyone understand a word I'm saying here?
布鲁迪先生
Mr. Brody!
这真的是太好了
Sallah. What a relief.
马库斯·布鲁迪
Marcus Brody, sir.
- 印第人呢？ - 他在奥地利
- But where is Indy?   - He's in Austria.
处理一点小事
A slight detour.
你一个人吗？
You are on your own?
对  不要惊慌  一切都在控制中
Yes, but don't panic. Everything's under control.
补给品都安排好了吗？
Have you, have you arranged our supplies?
是的  我们到底要去哪里？
Yes, of course. But where are we going?
跟着这张地图走就对了
This map will show you.
画出它的人是...
It was drawn by...
布鲁迪先生
Mr. Brody.
欢迎光临伊斯肯德隆
Welcome to Iskenderun.
博物馆馆长派车来接你
The director of the Museum of Antiquities has sent a car for you.
请吧  先生
Well, your servant, sir.
我跟他是一起的
And I am his.
请跟我来
Follow me, please.
看来我在这里很有名
My reputation precedes me.
本地没有博物馆
There is no museum in Iskenderun.
请把文件拿出来
Papers, please.
你要报纸？没问题
Papers? Of course.
- 快跑  - 是的
- Run.   - Yes.
报纸？应该就在这里
Papers. Got it here.
我刚刚才看完
Just finished reading it myself.
- 快跑  - 是的
- Run.   - Yes.
埃及邮报的早报版  快跑
Egyptian Mail, morning edition. Run.
你刚刚说...
Did you say...
快跑
Run!
快点上来
Okay, okay, quick, quick, quick!
从后门出去
Find the back door! Find the back door!
这真的是太夸张了
Intolerable.
史奈德博士  你得立刻回柏林
Dr. Schneider. Message from Berlin. You must return immediately.
- 有一个会议在亚利安文化中心召开  - 那么？
- A rally at the Institute of Aryan Culture.   - So?
高层要求你亲临参加
Your presence on the platform is requested at the highest level.
谢谢  伊斯肯德隆见
Thank you, Herr Oberst. I will meet you at Iskenderun.
把日记送到帝国博物馆
Take this diary to the Reichmuseum in Berlin.
向他们报告我们的进展
It will show them our progress, ahead of schedule.
没有那张地图  它根本一点作用都没有
Without the map, I'm afraid it's no better than a souvenir.
让我杀了他们
Let me kill them now.
不行
No.
如果找不到那几页日记
If we fail to recover the pages from Brody,
我们需要他们的帮助
we'll need them alive.
博士说的话永远都是对的
Always do what the doctor orders.
别那样子看我
Don't look at me like that.
我们都想找到圣杯
We both wanted the Grail.
我愿意不计代价找到它
I would have done anything to get it.
你也一样
You would have done the same.
我很遗憾你会那么想
I'm sorry you think so.
我不会忘了跟你在一起的欢愉
I can't forget how wonderful it was.
谢谢
Thank you.
我也觉得很愉快
It was rather wonderful.
史奈德博士
Dr. Schneider.
车子已经准备好了
Your car is waiting.
奥地利人都是这样说再见的
That's how Austrians say good-bye.
德国人是这样说再见的  琼斯博士
And this is how we say good-bye in Germany, Dr. Jones.
我比较喜欢奥地利人的方式
I liked the Austrian way better.
我也一样
So did I.
快把绳子松开
Let's try and get these ropes loose.
我们得比纳粹更早找到马库斯
We've got to get to Marcus before the Nazis do.
你说过他提早两天出发  他可以隐身在人潮中
You said he had two days' start. That he would blend in. Disappear.
你在开玩笑吗？那是我瞎编的
Are you kidding? I made that up.
他连在博物馆里都会迷路
You know Marcus. He got lost once in his own museum.
你摸得到我外套的左边口袋吗？
Can you try and reach my left jacket pocket?
你要我找什么？
What am I looking for?
我的幸运护身符
My lucky charm.
我只摸到一个打火机
Feels like a cigarette lighter.
快把绳子烧断
Try and burn through the ropes.
太好了
Very good.
我想告诉你一件事
I ought to tell you something.
现在不是感伤的时候  出去再说
Don't get sentimental now, Dad. Save it till we get out of here.
地板着火了
The floor's on fire.
- 看到了吗？ - 什么？
- See? - What?
椅子也着火了
And the chair.
快一点
Move! Move it out of here! Go!
到桌子旁边去
It's scorching the table! Fast!
- 快一点  - 好
- Move!    - Okay!
我们抓到了马库斯·布鲁迪
Well, we have Marcus Brody,
更重要的是  我们找到了地图
but more important, we have the map.
"听从元帅的命令"
"By the personal command of the Fehrer.
"是成功的关键要素"
"Secrecy essential to success.
"消灭美国阴谋者"
"Eliminate the American conspirators."
德国人已对琼斯父子宣战
Germany has declared war on the Jones boys.
- 爸  - 什么事？
- Dad!    - What?
到壁炉那边去
Head for the fireplace!
我有办法将绳子松开
I think I can get these ropes off.
情况还是没有改善
Our situation has not improved.
听着  我快把绳子拉开来了
Listen, Dad, I'm almost free.
警报
Alarm!
这真的是太夸张了
This is intolerable.
我自由了  爸
I'm out, Dad.
做得好  儿子
Well done, boy.
快来吧  爸
Come on, Dad.
这是死路
Dead end.
这里一定有暗门
There's got to be a...A secret door or a...
或秘密通道
Passageway or something.
我发现只要坐下来好好思考
I find that if I just sit down and think...
爸
Dad!
答案自然而然就会出现
...the solution presents itself.
太棒了  又是船
Great. More boats.
你平常都是这么过日子的吗？
You say this has been just another typical day for you, huh?
不  今天的情况还算不错
No! But better than most.
快来吧  爸
Come on, Dad. Come on.
什么？
What about the boat?
我们不搭船吗？
We're not going on the boat?
琼斯
Jones!
站住  站住
Halt! Halt!
(威尼斯-柏林)
- 快停车  - 什么？
- Stop!   - What?
快停车
Stop! Stop!
你走错方向了  我们得到柏林去
You're going the wrong way. We have to get to Berlin.
布鲁迪在这边
Brody's this way.
我的日记在柏林
My diary's in Berlin.
我们不需要那本日记
We don't need the diary, Dad.
地图在布鲁迪手上
Marcus has the map.
那本日记里不只画了地图
There is more in the diary than just the map.
好吧  爸  快告诉我
All right, Dad. Tell me.
找到圣杯的人  必须面对最后的挑战
Well, he who finds the Grail must face the final challenge.
什么最后的挑战？
What final challenge?
你得通过三项狡猾的考验
Three devices of such lethal cunning.
- 你是指机关吗？ - 没错
- Booby traps? - Yes.
我找到了能让我们安全通过的线索
But I found the clues that will safely take us through,
就在圣安生编年史里
in the Chronicles of St. Anselm.
到底是什么？
Well, what are they?
你不记得了吗？
Can't you remember?
我把它们写在日记里  那样就不必花脑筋去记了
I wrote them down in my diary so that I wouldn't have to remember.
一半的德国大军都在追我们  你想到柏林去？
Half the German army's on our tail, and you want me to go to Berlin?
- 深入虎穴？ - 没错
- Into the lion's den?   - Yes.
最重要的事就是找到圣杯
The only thing that matters is the Grail.
马库斯该怎么办？
What about Marcus?
他会同意我的做法
Marcus would agree with me.
两个无私的殉教者
Two selfless martyrs.
去他的耶稣基督
Jesus Christ.
那是教训你不该亵渎上帝
That's for blasphemy.
寻找圣杯  不是为了寻找考古证据
The quest for the Grail is not archeology.
这是一场正邪战争
It's a race against evil.
如果它落入纳粹手中
If it is captured by the Nazis,
黑暗大军将会征服全世界
the armies of darkness will march all over the face of the Earth.
你了解吗？
Do you understand me?
你太着迷了  爸
This is an obsession, Dad.
我从来就不了解  真的不了解
I never understood it. Never.
妈妈也不了解
Neither did Mom.
不  她了解
Yes, she did.
问题出在她太了解了
Only too well.
我真的很遗憾  她对我隐瞒她的病情
Unfortunately, she kept her illness from me
我知道时  她已经没救了
until all I could do was mourn her.
(柏林-威尼斯)
孩子  我们是这个浊世里的一股清流
My boy, we are pilgrims in an unholy land.
博士
Freulein Doctor.
- 它在哪里？ - 你怎么会到这里来？
- Where is it?    - How did you get here?
它在哪里？我要那本日记
Where is it? I want it.
你为日记跑回来？为什么？
You came back for the book? Why?
我爸爸不希望它被烧掉
My father didn't want it incinerated.
你真的以为我是那种人？
Is that what you think of me?
我相信的是圣杯  而不是纳粹
I believe in the Grail, not the swastika.
你也是圣杯的敌人
But you stood up to be counted with the enemy of everything that the Grail stands for.
谁会在乎你在想什么？
Who gives a damn what you think?
你就在乎
You do.
我会狠狠地教训你
All I have to do is squeeze.
我会放声大叫
All I have to do is scream.
到手了  我们快离开这里吧
I've got it. Let's get the hell out of here.
(阿道夫·希特勒)
(柏林机场)
- 你买到票了吗？ - 我买了最快离开德国的机票
- What did you get?   - I don't know. First available flight out of Germany.
很好
Good.
我们成功了
Well, we made it.
一旦我们顺利升空  把德国人全都甩在脑后
When we're airborne, with Germany behind us,
我才会说我跟你有同感
then I'll share that sentiment.
放轻松
Relax.
请把票拿出来
Tickets, please.
您好  亨利·琼斯
Guten Tag, Herny Jones.
请把票拿出来
Tickets, please.
我们应该离开这里
We should get out of here.
他没有票
No ticket.
我有票
Ticket.
- 我的票在这里  - 我的票在这里
- Ticket!   - Ticket!
分享你的冒险经历  是相当有趣的经验
You know, sharing your adventures is an interesting experience.
我们分享的不只是这个
That's not all we shared.
那真的是太丢脸了  你老到可以当她的爷爷
It's disgraceful. You're old enough to be her fa...Her grandfather.
我跟其他男人一样都是人
Well, I'm as human as the next man.
我是她的下一个男人
I was the next man.
没错  你就像是在黑暗中航行的船只
Of course. Well... Ships that pass in the night.
还记得我们上一次坐下来喝一杯的事吗？
Do you remember the last time we had a quiet drink?
当时我喝的是牛奶
I had a milkshake.
我们聊了什么事？
What did we talk about?
我们根本没说话
We didn't talk.
我们从不聊天
We never talked.
你在责备我吗？
Do I detect a rebuke?
我只是很遗憾  我们相依为命
A regret. It was just the two of us, Dad.
成长的路对我来说太寂寞了
It was a lonely way to grow up. For you, too.
如果你跟其他老爸一样平凡
If you'd been an ordinary, average father,
或许你就会了解
like the other guys' dads, you'd have understood that.
事实上  我是个很棒的父亲
Actually, I was a wonderful father.
什么时候？
When?
我曾告诉过你要乖乖吃饭
Did I ever tell you to eat up? Go to bed?
睡觉跟做功课吗？
Wash your ears? Do your homework?
从来没有  我尊重你的隐私  还教你要靠自己
No. I respected your privacy, and I taught you self-reliance.
你只教我  我是全世界最不重要的人
What you taught me was that I was less important to you
连死了五百年的人都比我重要
than people who'd been dead for 500 years in another country.
我非常清楚
And I learned it so well
二十年来我们没有说过几次话
that we've hardly spoken for 20 years.
你会离开  是因为你对考古学产生了兴趣
You left just when you were becoming interesting.
难以置信
Unbelievable.
- 爸  你怎么能...  - 非常好
- Dad, how can you... - Very well.
现在我就在你面前
I'm here now.
你想跟我聊什么？
What do you want to talk about?
呃  我...
Well, I...
我想不出来
I can't think of anything.
你为什么要抱怨？
Then what are you complaining about?
我们还有工作要做
Look, we have work to do.
到了亚力山勒达后  我们就得面对三个挑战
When we get to Alexandretta, we will face three challenges.
第一是"上帝的气息,只有忏悔的人才能通过"
The first, "The Breath of God. Only the penitent man will pass."
第二是"上帝的话语"
Second, "The Word of God.
"跟着上帝脚步的人才能通过"
"Only in the footsteps of God will he proceed."
第三是"上帝的道路"
Third, "The Path of God.
"只有从狮子头一跃而过的人 才能证明他的价值"
"Only in the leap from the lion's head will he prove his worth."
那是什么意思？
What does that mean?
我不知道  我们会查出来的
I don't know. We'll find out.
飞船在转弯
We're turning around.
他们要带我们回德国去
They're taking us back to Germany.
我还以为他们不会这么快发现无线电坏了
Well, I thought it would take them a lot longer to figure out the radio was dead.
快走
Come on, Dad. Move!
快一点  爸
Come on, Dad. Come on!
我不知道你会开飞机
I didn't know you could fly a plane.
我的确会开飞机
Fly, yes.
但我不会降落
Land, no.
你得使用那把机关枪
Dad, you're going to have to use the machine gun.
快点准备好
Get it ready.
十一点钟方向
Eleven o'clock!
爸  十一点钟方向
Dad, eleven o'clock!
十一点钟方向怎么了？
What happens at eleven o'clock?
十二点钟  十一点钟  十点钟
Twelve, eleven, ten.
十一点钟方向  快开火
Eleven o'clock, fire!
爸  我们中弹了吗？
Dad, are we hit?
可以那么说
More or less.
儿子  对不起
Son, I'm sorry.
他们打中了我们
They got us.
抓紧了  爸  我们要降落了
Hang on, Dad. We're going in!
- 降落得很漂亮  - 谢谢夸奖
- Nice landing.    - Thanks.
他们想要杀死我们
Those people are trying to kill us!
我知道
I know, Dad!
对我来说  这是个全新的经验
Well. It's a new experience for me.
我常常遇到这种事
It happens to me all the time.
这真的是太夸张了
This is intolerable!
他们越来越近了
This could be close.
快一点  儿子
Faster, boy! Faster!
他们最多也只能追到这里
Well, they don't come any closer than that!
爸  他就快飞回来了
Dad, he's coming back!
我突然想起我的查理曼大帝
I suddenly remembered my Charlemagne.
"让我的大军成为石头  树木跟天空的鸟儿"
"Let my armies be the rocks and the trees and the birds in the sky."
(哈太共和国)
这是琼斯博士被撕去的那几页日记
These pages are taken from Professor Jones' diary, Your Highness,
里面有一幅地图
and they include a map
指出了圣杯的位置
that pinpoints the exact location of the Grail.
圣杯即将落入我们手里
As you can see, the Grail is all but in our hands.
但没有你的许可
However, Your Highness,
我们无法通过你的领地
we would not think of crossing your soil without your permission,
也无法带着圣杯离开你的边界
nor of removing the Grail from your borders without suitable compensation.
你们带了什么东西来？
What have you brought?
全是一些很珍贵的东西  殿下
Precious valuables, Your Highness,
这都是德国有钱的家族捐出来的东西
donated by some of the finest families in all of Germany.
劳斯莱斯幽灵二型
Rolls-Royce Phantom Two.
4.3公升  30匹马力  6汽缸引擎
Four-point-three liter, 30 horsepower, six-cylinder engine,
配备史洛姆伯格公司制造的下拖式化油器
with Stromberg downdraft carburetor.
时速从零加速到一百里
Can go from zero to 100 kilometers an hour
只需要12.5秒
in 12.5 seconds.
我最喜欢的是它的颜色
And I even like the color.
钥匙已经都插好了  殿下
The keys are in the ignition, Your Highness.
我会提供你们骆驼  马
You shall have camels, horses,
武装随从  补给品
an armed escort, provisions,
沙漠车辆跟坦克
desert vehicles and tanks.
谢谢你
You're welcome.
没时间了
We have no time to lose.
印第安纳·琼斯跟他父亲已经逃走了
Indiana Jones and his father have escaped.
我们得从这边走
We go this way.
快把那头骆驼拉开
Get that camel out of the way.
马库斯怎么了？
What happened to Marcus, Sallah?
今天下午他们要越过沙漠
They set out across the desert this afternoon.
还带着他同行
I believe they took Mr. Brody with them.
他们拿到地图了
Now they have the map.
在这场比赛中
And in this sort of race,
第二名还是拿不到奖牌
there's no silver medal for finishing second.
你想喝点水吗  马库斯？
Care to wet your whistle, Marcus?
我宁愿往你脸上吐口水
I'd rather spit in your face.
但我并没有那么做...
But as I haven't got any spit...
圣杯就在三到四里的范围内
Must be within three or four miles.
不然的话  就是我们走错路了
Otherwise we are off the map.
马库斯  我们就快要找到
Well, Marcus, we are on the brink of the recovery of
人类史上最伟大的圣物
the greatest artifact in the history of mankind.
你们是不自量力  在帮自己找麻烦
You're meddling with powers you cannot possibly comprehend.
我看到布鲁迪了
I see Brody.
他似乎没事
He seems okay.
他们还把坦克搬来了
They've got a tank.
还有一把小型火炮
Six-pound gun.
你在做什么？快趴下
What do you think you're doing there? Get down!
爸  我们不在射击范围内
Dad, we're well out of range.
那是我大舅子的车
That car belonged to my brother-in-law.
快来吧
Come on, come on!
上面没有人
I can't see anyone up there.
可能不是琼斯吧
Maybe it wasn't even Jones.
不  一定是他
No, it is him, all right.
他就在附近
He's here somewhere.
把布鲁迪带到坦克里
Put Brody in the tank.
阳光这么强
Well, in this sun,
没有交通工具  他们是死定了
without transportation, they're as good as dead.
真的是琼斯
It's Jones, all right.
- 他们是谁？ - 谁在乎？
- Now, who are all these people?    - Who cares?
他们能帮我们缠住陶诺文
As long as they're keeping Donovan busy.
爸  你留在这里  我们去弄交通工具
Dad, you stay here while Sallah and I organize some transportation.
- 我去找马  - 我去找骆驼
- I'm going after those horses.   - I'll take the camels.
- 不要骆驼  - 但是 印第...
- I don't need camels. - But, Indy...
我绝不骑骆驼
No camels.
他是什么人？
Who is he?
他是上帝派来的使者
A messenger from God.
为了对抗邪恶
For the unrighteous,
圣杯装载了永恒的诅咒
the Cup of Life holds everlasting damnation.
马库斯
Marcus!
"只要能找回圣杯"
"Genius of the Restoration..."
"就能够唤醒人心"
"Aid our own resuscitation."
亨利  你在这里做什么？
Henry, what are you doing here?
我来救你
It's a rescue, old boy. Come on.
搜他的身
Search him.
你的日记里到底写了什么东西？
What is in this book? That miserable little diary of yours.
那本日记毫无用处
We have the map. The book is useless.
你却跑回柏林找它
And yet you come all the way back to Berlin to get it.
为什么？
Why?
你在隐瞒什么？
What are you hiding?
那本日记能告诉你哪些我们不知道的事？
What does the diary tell you that it doesn't tell us?
它告诉我像你们这样的大混蛋
It tells me that goose-stepping morons like yourself
应该多看书而不是把书给烧掉
should try reading books instead of burning them.
上校
Colonel!
琼斯要逃走了
Jones is getting away.
不可能的
I think not,
陶诺文先生
Herr Donovan.
不是那个琼斯  是另一个琼斯
Not that Jones, the other Jones!
萨拉  我不要骆驼
Sallah, I said no camels!
你却找了五头骆驼来  你不会数数吗？
That's five camels. Can't you count?
它们可以代替车子
Compensation for my brother-in-law's car.
何况你父亲跟布鲁迪...
Indy, your father and Brody...
我爸在哪里？
Where's my father?
他在那头钢铁怪兽的肚子里
They have them. In the belly of that steel beast.
开枪
Fire!
爸 爸
Dad! Dad!
- 爸  - 二世
- Dad! - Junior?
二世
Junior?
Junior!
爸
Dad!
爸  快出来
Dad! Get out!
亨利  那枝笔...
Henry, the pen...
- 什么？ - 你没看见吗？
- What? - But don't you see?
笔比枪还有力
The pen is mightier than the sword.
看看你做的好事
Look what you did.
这是战争
It's war.
我不是告诉过你我们是来救你的吗？
Didn't I tell you it was a rescue?
- 爸  - 嗯？
- Dad!    - Yeah?
这就是考古学研究？
You call this archeology?
快离开这儿
Get out of there, Dad.
我要怎么下去？
How does one get off this thing?
马库斯在哪里？
Where's Marcus?
爸
Dad!
抓紧了  爸
Hang on, Dad!
印第的爹  快把手伸过来
Father of Indy, give me your hand!
萨拉
Sallah!
快去救我爸
Get Dad!
快把手伸过来
Give me your hand!
二世
Junior!
印第
Indy!
我的天啊
Oh, God.
我失去他了
I've lost him.
我还来不及告诉他
And I never told him anything.
我只是还没有准备好
I just wasn't ready, Marcus.
只要五分钟就够了
Five minutes would have been enough.
我还以为我失去你了  儿子
I thought I'd lost you, boy!
我也是那么想  爸
I thought you had too, sir.
那么...
Well...
做得好  快走吧
Well done. Come on.
我们得出发了
Let's go, then.
你干嘛还坐在那里休息？我们就快到了
Why are you sitting there resting when we're so near the end?
来吧
Come on, let's go!
新月峡谷
The Canyon of the Crescent Moon.
赫蒙特  又有人自愿牺牲
Helmut, another volunteer!
我没想到还能再见到你
I never expected to see you again.
我天生黏人  喜欢吃回头草
I'm like a bad penny, I always turn up.
快退后  史奈德博士  给琼斯博士一点空间
Step back now, Dr. Schneider. Give Dr. Jones some room.
他得帮我们找到圣杯
He's going to recover the Grail for us.
不可能吗？你觉得呢？准备好要在历史上留名了吗？
Impossible? What do you say, Jones? Ready to go down in history?
留什么名？跟你一样变成纳粹走狗？
As what? A Nazi stooge like you?
纳粹？
The Nazis?
你的眼界就这么小吗？
Is that the limit of your vision?
纳粹想在圣杯传奇中留名
The Nazis want to write themselves into the Grail legend,
他们想占领全世界
take on the world.
我没有意见
Well, they're welcome.
但我要的是圣杯
But I want the Grail itself.
那个杯子拥有长生不老的力量
The cup that gives everlasting life.
希特勒可以拥有全世界  但他无法将它带入坟墓里
Hitler can have the world, but he can't take it with him.
我要的是长生不老  他的愿望真的太渺小了
I'm going to be drinking my own health when he's gone the way of the dodo.
圣杯是我的
The Grail is mine,
你得帮我找到它
and you're going to get it for me.
开枪杀了我  对你一点好处都没有
Shooting me won't get you anywhere.
你知道吗？
You know something, Dr. Jones?
你说的对
You're absolutely right.
爸
Dad?
二世
Junior...
- 不  - 快后退
- No!    - Get back!
你死了就救不了他
You can't save him when you're dead!
只有圣杯的力量能救他
The healing power of the Grail is the only thing that can save your father now.
你该问问自己相信什么
It's time to ask yourself what you believe.
"上帝的气息"
"The Breath of God.
"只有忏悔的人才能通过"
"Only the penitent man will pass."
忏悔的人才能通过
"The penitent man will pass."
The penitent man will pass.
忏悔的人...
The penitent man...
"只有忏悔的人才能通过"
"Only the penitent man will pass."
忏悔的人才能通过  忏悔的人 忏悔的人
The penitent man will pass. The penitent, penitent...
忏悔的人...
The penitent man...
The penitent man... The penitent...
忏悔的人会在上帝面前卑躬屈膝
The penitent man is humble before God.
忏悔的人...
Penitent. Penitent...
忏悔的人？
The penitent man...
忏悔的人会在上帝面前卑躬屈膝
Penitent man is humble, kneels before God.
快跪下
Kneel!
我过关了
I'm through!
我们过关了
We're through.
他没事
He's all right.
不
No.
第二个挑战是"上帝的话语"
The second challenge: "The Word of God."
"跟着上帝脚步的人才能通过"
"Only in the footsteps of God will he proceed."
上帝的话语？
The Word of God...
The Word of...
跟着上帝脚步？
Proceed in the footsteps of the Word.
- 上帝的话语  - 亨利  别说话
- "The Word of God..."   - No, Henry. Try not to talk.
是上帝的名字
The name of God...
耶和华
Jehovah.
但在拉丁文中  耶和华的第一个字母是"I"
But in the Latin alphabet, Jehovah begins with an "I."
"J"
天啊
Oh, dear.
笨蛋
Idiot!
拉丁文中  耶和华的字首是"I"
In Latin, Jehovah starts with an "I."
"I"
"I".
"E"
"E".
"H"
"H".
"O"
"O".
"V"
"V".
"A"
"A".
"上帝的道路"
"The Path of God."
"只有从狮子头一跃而过的人"
"Only in the leap from the lion's head
"才能证明他的价值"
"will he prove his worth."
不可能的  谁都没办法跳过去
Impossible, nobody can jump this.
印第
Indy!
你得快一点
Indy, you must hurry!
快一点
Come quickly!
你得靠信心跳过去
It's a leap of faith.
你得相信上帝  孩子
You must believe, boy.
你得相信上帝
You must believe.
我就知道你一定会来
I knew you'd come,
我已经没有力气了
but my strength has left me.
你是谁？
Who are you?
我是三兄弟中唯一还活着的人
The last of three brothers
我们发誓会找到圣杯
who swore an oath to find the Grail
并且好好看守它
and to guard it.
那是七百年前的事了
That was 700 years ago.
我等了很久
A long time to wait.
就一个骑士来说  你的打扮很奇怪
You're strangely dressed, for a knight.
事实上我不是骑士
I'm not exactly...
你是什么意思？
A knight? What do you mean?
上帝会选上我
I was chosen
因为我是最勇敢而有价值的人
because I was the bravest, the most worthy.
我的荣耀将传给下一个来到这里向我单挑的人
The honor was mine until another came to challenge me to single combat.
因为你打赢了我  我得把它传给你
I pass it to you who vanquished me.
我没有时间解释了  但...
Listen, I don't have time to explain, but...
是哪一个呢？
Which one is it?
你得从中挑选一个
You must choose,
但你得做出明智的选择
but choose wisely.
因为真正的圣杯会让你长生不老
For as the true Grail will bring you life,
假圣杯会带走你的生命
the false Grail will take it from you.
我不是历史学家
I'm not a historian.
不知道它长什么样子
I have no idea what it looks like.
是哪一个？
Which one is it?
让我来选吧
Let me choose.
谢谢你  博士
Thank you, Doctor.
太棒了
Yes.
它比我想像中还漂亮
It's more beautiful than I'd ever imagined.
这的确是王中之王的杯子
This certainly is the cup of the King of Kings.
敬长生不老
Eternal life.
我是怎么了？
What is happening to me?
发生了什么事？
Tell me, what is happening?
他的选择...
He chose
是错的
poorly.
圣杯不可能用黄金做成
It would not be made out of gold.
它是木匠使用的杯子
That's the cup of a carpenter.
只有一个方法能查个清楚
There's only one way to find out.
你做出了明智的选择
You have chosen wisely.
但圣杯绝对不能越过大封印
But the Grail cannot pass beyond the Great Seal.
那是唯一的禁忌  跟长生不老的代价
That is the boundary and the price of immortality.
请把枪放下
Drop your guns. Please.
爸  快起来
Dad, come on, get to your feet.
我们找到圣杯了
We have got it. Come on!
艾儿莎  不要动
Elsa! Elsa, don't move!
它是你跟我的  印第
It's ours, Indy, yours and mine.
不要越过封印
Elsa, don't cross the Seal.
骑士警告过我们  不能从那里把圣杯带走
The knight warned us not to take the Grail from here.
二世
Junior!
艾儿莎
Elsa...
别那么做  艾儿莎
Elsa, don't. Elsa...
艾儿莎
Elsa...
把另一只手伸过来 我拉不住你了
Give me your other hand, honey. I can't hold you!
我可以摸到它
I can reach it. I can reach it.
把另一只手伸过来
Elsa, give me your hand. Give me your other hand!
艾儿莎
Elsa!
二世  把另一只手伸过来
Junior, give me your other hand!
我拉不住你了
I can't hold on.
我可以摸到它
I can get it.
只差一点我就能拿到了  爸
I can almost reach it, Dad.
印第安纳
Indiana...
放弃吧
Let it go.
爸
Dad...
走吧  爸
Please, Dad.
艾儿莎并不相信圣杯是真的
Elsa never really believed in the Grail.
她以为自己拿到了宝物
She thought she'd found a prize.
你有什么发现呢  爸？
What did you find, Dad?
我吗？
Me?
我找到了上帝的光荣
Illumination.
你又有什么发现呢  二世？
And what did you find, Junior?
"二世"？爸...
"Junior"? Dad...
你为什么老叫他二世？
Please, what does it always mean, this... This "Junior"?
那是他的名字  亨利·琼斯二世
That's his name: Henry Jones, Junior.
我比较喜欢印第安纳
I like Indiana.
我们家的狗就叫印第安纳
We named the dog Indiana.
我们可以回家了吗？
May we go home now, please?
你跟你家的狗同名？
The dog? You are named after the dog?
我跟那只狗有很多美好的回忆
I've got a lot of fond memories of that dog.
- 准备好了吗？- 我准备好了
- Ready?  - Ready.
印第  亨利  跟我来  我认得路
Indy! Henry! Follow me. I know the way!
他连在博物馆里都会迷路  不是吗？
Got lost in his own museum, huh?
你走前面  二世
After you, Junior.
遵命  爸爸
Yes, sir.